<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?>


<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="loc.08491"> 
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    
    <title level="m" type="main" rend="bracketed">y Morning</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
    <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
    <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
    <editor>Matt Cohen</editor>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
     
     <persName xml:id="kmh">Kenneth Michael Hoover</persName>
    </respStmt>
    <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
    <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
    <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition>
     <date>2025</date>
    </edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    
    <distributor xml:id="wwa">The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
    <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
    <availability>
     <p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain exceptions, public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation of derivative works without permission, or authorization, of the former copyright owners.</p>
     <p>
      The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and is governed by a
      <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref>
      (CC BY 4.0). Permission to reproduce the graphic images of the original item has been granted by the owners of the original for this publication only.</p>
    </availability>
    

   <idno>loc.08491</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project" target="#dat1"><!-- THE CONTENTS OF THIS NOTE WILL BE WRITTEN BY EDITORS AT A LATER STAGE OF THE PROCESS --></note>
    
     <note type="work_relations" target="xxx.00480" cert="high">
      <p></p>
     </note>
   </notesStmt>
   
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <author xml:id="ww">Whitman, Walt</author>
     
     <title>November Boughs (1888); Newspaper clippings with corrections and notations</title>  
     
     <date when="1888" cert="high">1888</date>
     
     <idno type="callno">loc.08491</idno>
     
     <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839-1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
     
     <note>Transcribed from digital images of the original.</note>
      
     <note type="project" target="#rel01">The prose drafted on the back of these and several other related manuscript leaves includes ideas and phrases that resemble those used in "Unnamed Lands," a poem published first in the 1860 edition of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>.</note>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <handNotes>
    <handNote medium="letterpress" xml:id="h01" resp="#unk1"><name>Unknown1</name></handNote>
    <handNote medium="blue pencil" xml:id="h02" resp="#ww"/>
    <handNote medium="black ink" xml:id="h03" resp="#ww"/>
    <handNote medium="pencil" xml:id="h04" resp="#unk3"><name>Unknown3</name></handNote>
   </handNotes>
  </profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
 
 <change when="2025-03-03" who="#kmh">transcribed and encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>

 <text type="manuscript">
  <body>
   
   <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_kmh.00001.jpg" type="recto"/>
   <note type="editorial" place="left" hand="#h04">George &#10003;</note>
   <note type="authorial" place="top" hand="#h02">136</note>
   <p>y Morning, June 11&#8212;<del rend="overstrike" hand="#h03">On a sand</del><gap reason="cut away" extent="one word"/><del rend="overstrike" hand="#h03">the St. Clair flats, where we had been stuck for a couple of hours.</del>We pass<subst hand="#h03"><del rend="overstrike">e</del><add place="right" xml:id="a001">'</add></subst><add hand="#h03" place="right"><metamark function="add" target="#a001">&#711;</metamark></add>d down Lake Huron yesterday and last night, and between 4 and 5 o'clock this morning we ran on the "flats," and have been mainly trying, with the aid of a steam <gap reason="cut away" extent="one word"/> and a lumbering lighter, to get cl<gap reason="cut away" extent="three letters"></gap> again. The day is beautiful and th<gap reason="cut away" extent="four letters"/>er clear and calm. Night before last we stop<subst hand="#h03"><del rend="overstrike">ped</del><add place="right">t</add></subst> at Mackinaw, (the island and town,) and I went up on the old fort, one of the oldest stations in the Northwest. We expect to get to Buffalo by to-morrow. The tug has fasten<subst hand="#h03"><del rend="overstrike">e</del><add place="right" xml:id="a002">'</add></subst><add place="right" hand="#h02"><metamark function="add" target="#a002">&#711;</metamark></add>d lines to us, but some have been snap<subst hand="#h02"><del rend="overstrike">ped</del><add place="right">t</add></subst> and the others have no effect. We seem to be firmly imbedded in the sand. (With the exception of a larger boat and better accommodations, it amounts to about the same thing as a becalmment I underwent on the Mountauk voyage, East Long Island, last summer.)  Later.&#8212;We are off again&#8212;expect to reach Detroit before dinner.</p>
   <note type="editorial" place="left" hand="#h04"><del rend="overstrike">&#10003;</del></note>
   <p>We did not stop at Detroit. We are now on Lake Erie, jogging along at a good round pace. A couple of hours since we were on the river above.  Detroit seem<subst hand="#h03"><del rend="overstrike">e</del><add place="right" xml:id="a003">'</add></subst><add hand="#h03"><metamark function="add" target="#a003">&#711;</metamark></add>d to me a pretty place and thrifty. I especially liked the looks of the Canadian shore opposite and of the little village of Windsor, and, indeed, all along the banks of the river. From the shrubbery and the neat appearance of some of the cottages, I think it must have been settled by the French. While I now write we can see a little distance ahead the scene of the battle between Perry's fleet and the British during the last war with England. The lake looks to me like a fine sheet of water. We are having a beautiful day.</p>
   <p>June 12.&#8212;We stop<subst hand="#h03"><del rend="overstrike">ped</del><add place="right">t</add></subst> last evening at Cleveland, and though it was dark, I took the opportunity of rambling about the place; went up in the heart of the city and back to what appear<subst hand="#h03"><del rend="overstrike">e</del><add place="right" xml:id="a004">'</add></subst><add place="right" hand="#h03"><metamark function="add" target="#a004">&#711;</metamark></add>d to be the courthouse. The streets are unusually wide, and the buildings appear to be substantial and comfortable. We went down through Main street and found, some distance along, several squares of ground very prettily planted with trees and looking attractive enough. Return<subst hand="#h03"><del rend="overstrike">e</del><add place="right" xml:id="a005">'</add></subst><add place="right" hand="#h03">&#711;</add>d to the boat by way of the lighthouse on the hill.</p>
   <p>This morning we are making for Buffalo, being, I imagine, a little more than half across Lake Erie. The water is rougher than on Michigan or Huron. (On St. Clair it was smooth as glass.) The day is bright and dry, with a stiff head wind.</p>
   <p>We arrived in Buffalo on Monday evening; spent that night and a portion of next day going round the city exploring. Then got in the cars and went to
    <cb/>
    <note type="authorial" hand="#h02" rend="circled"><del rend="overstrike" hand="#h02">125</del></note>
    <fw>3</fw>
    Niagara; went under the falls&#8212;saw the whirlpool and all the other sights.</p>
   <p>Tuesday night started for Albany travel<subst hand="#h03"><del rend="overstrike">e</del><add place="left" xml:id="a006">'</add></subst><add place="left" hand="#h03"><metamark function="add" target="#a006">&#711;</metamark></add>d all night. From the time daylight afforded us a view of the country all seem<subst hand="#h03"><del rend="overstrike">e</del><add place="right" xml:id="a007">'</add></subst><add place="right" hand="#h03"><metamark function="add" target="#a007">&#711;</metamark></add>d very rich and well cultivated. Every few miles were large towns or villages.</p>
   <p>Wednesday late we arrived at Albany. Spent the evening in exploring. There was a political meeting (Hunker) at the capitol, but I pass<subst hand="#h03"><del rend="overstrike">e</del><add place="left" xml:id="a008"></add></subst><add place="left" hand="#h03"><metamark function="add" target="#a008">&#711;</metamark></add>d it by. Next morning I started down the Hudson in the Alida; arrived safely in New York that evening.</p>
   <signed><del rend="overstrike" hand="#h03">W<hi rend="small caps">ALT</hi> W<hi rend="small caps">HITMAN</hi>.</del></signed>
   
  
</body>
</text>
</TEI>