<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?> 
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nyp.00233">
    
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">In the latter part of the year 1765</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2010</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>nyp.00233</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>The text of the original item is in the public domain. The text encoding and editorial notes were created and/or prepared by the <hi rend="italic">Walt Whitman Archive</hi> and are licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0). Any reuse of the material should credit the <hi rend="italic">Walt Whitman Archive</hi>. Permission to reproduce the graphic images of the original item has been granted by the owners of the original for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project" target="#dat1"><!-- when was this manuscript written? --></note>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                    <persName xml:id="al">Ashley Lawson</persName> <persName xml:id="tj">Tim Jackson</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>          
                    <title>In the latter part of the year 1765</title> 
                    <!--     THE DATE INFORMATION IN THE NEXT LINE WILL BE ADDED BY AN EDITOR     -->
                    <!--<date xml:id="dat1" cert="****" when="/"> </date>-->
                    
                    <idno type="callno">HM 94RB-NBC (Whitman)</idno>
                    <orgName>The Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</orgName>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from our own digital image of the original manuscript.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            
        </fileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2010-12-09" who="#tj">Checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2010-09-27" who="#al">Transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text type="manuscript">
        
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nyp.00233.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
            <head type="main-derived">In the latter part of the year 1<subst><del rend="overwrite" seq="1">8</del><add place="over">7</add></subst>65</head>
            
            <note type="editorial" resp="unk" place="margintop"><add rend="pasteon">476.  WHITMAN (WALT,    ).  Auto. MS.  3 pp. 4to.  Describing the Stamp Act Riots in New York.</add></note>
            <note type="editorial" resp="unk" place="margintop">1861-2</note>
            
            <ab>In the latter part of the year 1<subst><del rend="overwrite" seq="1">8</del><add place="over">7</add></subst>65</ab>
            
            <add place="inline" rend="pasteon" hand="unk">while several English men-of-war were lying in the harbor, and after the fort had been put in a complete state of defence by the Royal governor, “the stamps,” conveyed in a merchant ship, arrived in the harbor of New-York.  The king’s stamp officer fearing the temper of the people, notwithstanding the means which had been adopted to overawe them, refused to receive the papers, much less to enter upon their distribution.  Upon his refusal, they were transferred, first to a ship of war, and subsequently to the governor’s quarters in Fort George.  But the people discovered the secret of their landing, and on the instant, hand-bills appeared on every corner, threatening all persons who received or delivered a stamp.  On the 31st of October the merchants held a meeting, and resolved not to import goods from England.  The next day the people hung the governor in effigy, in what is now the Park.  On the same evening they repaired to the fort, and found the soldiers on the rampart ready to receive them.  Nothing daunted, they marched to the gate, knocked and demanded admittance.  This was of course refused.  They then collected in the Bowling Green, and there, within pistol shot of the fort, built a bonfire, upon which they immolated the effigies of the governor along with his chariot, in which they fixed the effigy.  In the next newspaper appeared an emphatic semi-official announcement, that the governor “had not issued, and would not suffer to be issued, any of the stamps now in Fort George.”  The people were not satisfied; they declared that the stamps should be delivered out of the fort or they would take them away by force.  Finally, “after much negotiation,” they were delivered to the mayor and common council, and deposited in the City Hall.</add>
            
            <p>It seems that this neighborhood of New York, (of which Brooklyn then was, as it now is, a main constituent, if not indeed, as many would claim it
                to be, the better half,) took the lead in political movements, and really gave the cue to the great cause
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nyp.00233.002.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nyp.00233.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
                
                of American freedom and inseperable Union&#8212;the same then in <add place="supralinear" rend="insertion">the years that preceded</add> 1776, as now in 1861 and 2. The British government understood the importance
                of <del rend="overstrike">the</del> our colony perfectly well. There</p>
                
            <add rend="pasteon" place="inline" hand="unk">was a military force kept up there.  It was the head quarters of His Majesty's American Army.  Yet in 1766, it was boldly
                proclaimed under the very guns of the fort, that the British Parliament possessed not the shadow of a jurisdiction over America.  Nor did an
                apprehension of the men-of-war in the harbor, prevent the New-Yorkers from dragging one distributor of stamp from his hiding-place on the
                opposite side of the East-River.  They even compelled him to sign a resignation of his office before a public magistrate.  In the same record are
                accounts of the dashing movements of "the Liberty Boys," which <hi rend="underline">M<hi rend="small caps">arinus</hi> W<hi rend="small caps">illett</hi>, A<hi rend="small caps">lexander</hi> M<hi rend="small caps">c</hi>D<hi rend="small caps">ougall</hi>,</hi> and other patriots
                subsequently less distinguished than these men of mark, carried through with <del rend="overstrike"><gap reason="illegible" extent="about one word"/></del></add> <add place="marginright"
                    rend="insertion">spirit</add>
            
            <note type="authorial" place="marginleft" rend="circled">lower case</note><!-- [TJ] Is there a way to make this direction explicit, as it pertains to the underlined text? -->
            
            <p>The sending over of these stamps <add place="supralinear" rend="insertion">seems to have</add> made the people of Brooklyn and New York <del
                rend="overstrike">furious</del> <add place="supralinear" rend="insertion"><del rend="overstrike">fr</del>antic to a degree that can hardly now be realized.</add>.  We have before us
            as we write a stern <add place="supralinear" rend="insertion">old</add> remonstrance against it signed by over one hundred leading merchants of
                the time&#8212;many of them residents, or owners of farms, in Kings County.  Among others appear the names of Comfort Sands, and of Messrs. Lott,
                
                <note type="editorial" resp="unk" place="marginbottom">54R0888</note> 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="nyp.00233.004.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                
                <note type="editorial" resp="unk" place="margintop">NYPL</note>
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="nyp.00233.005.jpg" type="recto"/>
                
                Duyckman, Bogert, Walton, Lefferts, Kissam, Remsen, and Van Voorhis. Of the leading property owners and merchants of Brooklyn and New York, during the days of the Revolution, it must
                <add rend="pasteon" place="inline" hand="unk">be remembered, that it was the community which they <del rend="overstrike"><gap reason="illegible" extent="one word"/></del> represented, <del rend="overstrike"><gap reason="illegible"
                    extent="two words"/>THE MERCHANTS OF NEW YORK</del><!-- [TJ] Unsure of "THE MERCHANTS"? --> <del rend="overstrike"><add place="margineright" rend="unmarked">they</add></del> who were the first to enter into the famous non-importation agreement,
                    which, being followed by the other colonies, did more than any other movement to produce the repeal of the stamp act.  <del rend="overstrike">And</del> <subst><del rend="overstrike" seq="1">t</del><add
                        place="over" rend="overwrite">T</add></subst>hat success gave heart to the country for bolder movements.&#8212;<del rend="overstrike"><gap reason="illegible" extent="two to three
                            letters"/></del></add></p>
            
            <p>&#182; And while the merchants and property owners fought the attempt to intrude stamps &#38;c upon them by legal <del rend="overstrike"><unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#al">remo</unclear></del>
                documents and remonstrances, the common people <add place="supralinear" rend="insertion">in New York and Long Island</add> <del rend="overstrike">here</del> made direct attacks upon the offending officials. No
                stamp&#8209;distributor<del rend="overstrike">'</del>s' <subst><del rend="overstrike" seq="1">life</del><add place="supralinear" rend="unmarked" seq="2">lives</add></subst> <subst><del rend="overstrike"
                    seq="1">was</del><add place="supralinear" rend="unmarked" seq="2">were</add></subst> safe here, and they had to flee to the British ships, or to Canada.
            </p>
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="nyp.00233.006.jpg" type="verso"/> 
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>




