<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="tex.00410"> 
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    
    <title level="m" type="main">Backward Glances over a Traveled road</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
    <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
    <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
    <editor>Matt Cohen</editor>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
     
     <persName xml:id="ew">Emma Whaley</persName>
    </respStmt>
    <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
    <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
    <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition>
     <date>2024</date>
    </edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    
    <distributor xml:id="wwa">The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
    <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
    <availability>
     <p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain exceptions, public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation of derivative works without permission, or authorization, of the former copyright owners.</p>
     <p>
      The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and is governed by a
      <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref>
      (CC BY 4.0). Permission to reproduce the graphic images of the original item has been granted by the owners of the original for this publication only.</p>
    </availability>
    

   <idno>tex.00410</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project" target="#dat1"><!-- THE CONTENTS OF THIS NOTE WILL BE WRITTEN BY EDITORS AT A LATER STAGE OF THE PROCESS --></note>
    
     <note type="work_relations" target="xxx.00410" cert="high">
      <p>Proof of "My Book and I" (with corrections), which is one of the essays that Whitman combined to form "A Backward Glance O'er Travel'd Roads," which first appeared in November Boughs (1888).</p>
     </note>
   </notesStmt>
   
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <author xml:id="ww">Whitman, Walt</author>
     
     <title>"Backward Glances over a Traveled Road" (see also Leaves of Grass), proof with corrections, undated, 7pp</title>  
     
     <date notBefore="1846" notAfter="1888" cert="medium"></date>
     
     <idno type="callno">	TXRC03-A4, series 1, container 1.2</idno>
     
     <orgName xml:id="tex">The Walt Whitman Collection, Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, The University of Texas at Austin</orgName>
     
     <note>Transcribed from digital images of the original.</note>
      
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <handNotes>
    <handNote medium="letterpress" xml:id="h01" resp="#unk1" scope="major"><name xml:id="unk1">Unknown 1</name></handNote>
    <handNote medium="black ink" xml:id="h02" resp="#ww" scope="minor"/>
    <handNote medium="pencil" xml:id="h03" resp="#unk2" scope="minor"><name xml:id="unk2">Unknown 2</name></handNote>
   </handNotes>
  </profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
 
 <change when="2025-01-30" who="#ew">transcribed and encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>

 <text type="manuscript">
  <body>
   
   <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="tex_am.00007_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
   
   <note type="archival" place="top" hand="#h03">f21- #15 File "A"</note>
   
   <note type="editorial" place="top">36</note>
   
   <head rend="italic"><subst hand="#h02"><del seq="1" rend="overstrike">MY BOOK AND I.</del><add seq="2" place="below" rend="underline">Backward Glances over a Traveled road</add></subst></head>
   <head type="sub" rend="italic">MY BOOK AND I.</head>
   
   <p>P<hi rend="smallcaps">ERHAPS</hi> the best of a song heard, or of any and all true love, or life's fairest episodes, or sailors', soldiers' trying scenes on land or sea, is the floating <hi rend="italic">r&#233;sum&#233;</hi> of them, or any of them, long afterwards, looking at the actualities away back past, with all their practical exci-tations gone. How the soul loves to hover over such reminiscences!</p>
   <p>So here I sit gossiping in the early candle-light of old age<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d001"><add place="right" hand="#h02"><metamark function="delete" target="#d001">d</metamark></add>,</del>&#11840;I and my book<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d002">,</del><add hand="#h02" place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d002">d</metamark></add>&#11840;casting backward glances over out travelled road. After completing, as it were, the journey (a varied jaunt of years, with many halts and gaps of intervals&#11840;or some lengthened ship-voyage, wherein more than once the last hour had apparently arrived, and we seemed cer-tainly going down, yet reaching port<add hand="#h02" place="inline">,</add> in a <subst hand="#h02"><del seq="1" rend="overstrike">certain fashion</del><add seq="2" place="right">sufficient way,</add></subst> through all discomfitures at last)&#11840;after completing my poems, and letting an inter-val elapse to settle them, I am curious to review all in the light of their own (at the time unconscious, or mostly unconscious) intentions, with certain unfoldings of thirty years they seek to embody. These lines, therefore, will probably blend the weft of first purposes and speculations with the warp of that experience afterwards, always bring-ing strange developments.</p>
   <p>Result of seven or eight stages and struggles extending through nearly thirty years, I look upon "Leaves of Grass," now finished to the end of its opportunities and powers, as my definitive <hi rend="italic">carte <del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d003">de</del><add hand="#h02" place="right"><metamark function="delete" target="#d003">d</metamark></add> visite</hi> to the coming generations of the New World, <add place="above"><metamark target="#a001">*</metamark></add> if I may assume to say so. That I have not gained the acceptance of my own time, but have fallen back on fond dreams of the future ("Still lives the song, through Reg-nar dies")<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d004">,</del><add hand="#h02" place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d004">d</metamark></add>&#11840;that from a worldly and business point of view "Leaves of Grass" has been worse than a failure<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d005">,</del><add hand="#h02" place="right"><metamark function="delete" target="#d005">d</metamark></add>&#11840;that after thirty years of trial public criticism on the book and myself as author of it shows marked anger and contempt more than anything else ("I find a solid line of enemies to you everywhere,"&#11840;letter from W. S. K., Boston, May 28, 1884)<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d006">,</del><add hand="#h02" place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d006">d</metamark></add>&#11840;and that solely for publishing it I have been the object of two or three pretty serious official buffetings<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d007">,</del><add hand="#h02" place="right"><metamark function="delete" target="#d007">d</metamark></add>&#11840;is all probably no more than I ought to have expected. I had my choice when I commenced. I bid neither for soft eulogies, big money returns, nor the approbation of ex-isting schools and conventions. As fulfilled, or partially fulfilled, the best comfort of the whole business (after a small band of the dearest
   <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
   <metamark target="#a002" xml:id="a001">*</metamark><note xml:id="a002" type="authorial" place="bottom">When Champollion, on his death-bed, handed to the printer the revised proof of his "Egyptian Grammar," he said gayly<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d008">,</del><add hand="#h02" place="right"><metamark function="delete" target="#d008">d</metamark></add> "Be careful of this,&#11840;it is my <hi rend="italic">carte de visite</hi> to posterity."</note>
   
   <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="tex_am.00014_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
   
   <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="tex_am.00015_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
    
    <note type="editorial" place="top"><hi rend="italic">MY BOOK AND I.</hi> 37</note>
   
   friends and upholders ever vouchsafed to man or cause<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d009">,</del><add hand="#h02" place="right"><metamark function="delete" target="#d009">d</metamark></add>&#11840;doubtless all the more faithful and uncompromising&#11840;this little phalanx!&#11840;for being so few) is that, unstopped and unwarped by any influence outside the soul within me, I have had my say entirely my own way, and put it unerringly on record<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d010">,</del><add hand="#h02" place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d010">d</metamark></add>&#11840;the value thereof to be decided by time.</p>
   <p>In calculating that decision, William O'Connor and Dr. Bucke are far more peremptory than I am. Behind all else that can be said, I consider "Leaves of Grass" and its theory experimental<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d011">,</del><add hand="#h02" place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d011">d</metamark></add>&#11840;as, in the deepest sense, I consider our American republic itself to be, with its theory. I think I have at least enough philosophy not to be too ab-solutely certain of any thing of any results. In the second place, the volume is a <hi rend="italic">sortie</hi><del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d012">,</del><add hand="#h02" place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d012">d</metamark></add>&#11840;whether to prove triumphant and conquer its field of aim and escape and construction, nothing less than a hundred years from now can fully answer. I consider the point that I have positively gained a hearing to far more than make up for any and all other lacks and withholdings. Essentially <hi rend="italic">that</hi> was from the first, and has remained throughout, the main object. Now it is achieved, I am certainly con-tent<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d013">ed</del><add hand="#h02" place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d013">d</metamark></add> to waive any otherwise momentous drawbacks, as of little account.</p>
   <p>After continued personal ambition and effort, as a young fellow, to enter with the rest into competition for the usual rewards, business, political, literary, etc.<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d014">,</del><add hand="#h02" place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d014">d</metamark></add>&#11840;to take part in the great <hi rend="italic">m&#234;l&#233;e</hi>, both for vic-tory's prize itself and to do some good<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d015">,</del><add hand="#h02" place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d015">d</metamark></add>&#11840;after years of those aims and pursuits, I found myself remaining possessed, at the age of thirty-three to thirty-five, with a special desire and conviction. Or rather, to be quite exact, a desire and conviction that had been more or less flitting through my previous life, or hovering on the flanks, hitherto, had steadily advanced to the front, defined itself, and finally dominated everything else. This was a feeling or ambition to articu-late and faithfully express in literary form<add hand="#h02" place="below"><metamark function="add" target="#a003">&#8248;</metamark></add><add hand="#h02" place="left" xml:id="a003">,<metamark function="emphasize" target="#a003">/</metamark></add> and uncompromisingly<add hand="#h02" place="below"><metamark function="add" target="#a004">&#8248;</metamark></add><add hand="#h02" place="right" xml:id="a004">,<metamark function="add" target="#a004">/</metamark></add> my own physical, emotional, moral, intellectual, and &#230;sthetic Personality, in the midst of, and tallying, the momentous spirit and facts of its imme-diate days and of current America<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d016">,</del><add hand="#h02" place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d016">d</metamark></add>&#11840;and to exploit that Personality in a far more candid and comprehensive sense than any hitherto book.</p>
   <p>Perhaps this is in brief<add hand="#h02" place="below"><metamark function="add" target="#a005">&#8248;</metamark></add><add hand="#h02" place="left" xml:id="a005">,<metamark function="emphasize" target="#a005">/</metamark></add> or suggests<add hand="#h02" place="below"><metamark function="add" target="#a006">&#8248;</metamark></add><add hand="#h02" place="left" xml:id="a006">,<metamark function="emphasize" target="#a006">/</metamark></add> all I have sought to do. Given the nineteenth century with the United States and what they furnish as area and points of view, "Leaves of Grass" is, or seeks to be, simply a faithful and doubtless self-willed record. In the midst of all it gives one man's&#11840;the author's&#11840;identity, ardors, observations, faiths, and thoughts, colored hardly at all with any<add hand="#h02" place="below"><metamark function="add" target="#a007">&#8248;</metamark></add><add hand="#h02" place="left" xml:id="a007">decided</add> coloring from other faiths, other authors, other identities or times. Plenty of songs had been sung<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d017">,</del><add hand="#h02" place="right"><metamark function="delete" target="#d017">d</metamark></add>&#11840;beautiful, matchless songs&#11840;adjusted to other lands than these&#11840;other days, another spirit and stage of evolution; but I would sing, and leave out or put
   
   <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="tex_am.000016_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
   
   <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="tex_am.00017_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
    
   <note type="editorial" place="top">38 <hi rend="italic">MY BOOK AND I.</hi></note>
    
   in, solely with reference to America and myself and to-day. Modern science and democracy seemed to be throwing out their challenge to Poetry to put them in its statements in contradistinction to the songs and myths of the past. As I see it now (perhaps too late), I have un-wittingly taken up that challenge and made an attempt at such state-ments,&#11840;which I certainly would not assume to do now, knowing more clearly what it means.</p>
   <p>For grounds for "Leaves of Grass," as poetry, I have abandoned the conventional themes, which do not appear in it: none of the stock ornamentation, or choice plots of love or war, or high, exceptional per-sonages of Old-World song; nothing, as I may say, for beauty's sake,&#11840;no legend, or myth, or romance, nor euphemism, nor rhyme. But the broadest average of humanity and its identities in the now ripening nineteenth century, and especially in each of their countless examples and practical occupations in the United States to day.</p>
   <p>One main contrast of the ideas behind every page of my verses, com-pared with established poems, is (as I have said once before) their dif-ferent relative attitude towards God, towards the objective universe, and still more(by reflection, confession, assumption, etc.) the quite changed attitude of the ego, the one changing or talking, towards himself and towards his fellow-humanity. It is certainly time for America, above all, to begin this readjustment in the scope of verse, for everything else has changed. As I write, I see in an article on Wordsworth, in one of the current English magazines, the lines, "A few weeks ago an eminent French critic said that, owing to the special tendency to science and to its all-devouring force, poetry would cease to be read in fifty years." But I anticipate the very contrary. Only a firmer, vastly broader, new area begins to exist&#11840;nay, is already formed&#11840;to which the poetic genius must emigrate. Whatever may have been the case in years gone by, the true use for the imaginative faculty of modern times is to give ulti-mate vivification to facts, to science, and to common lives, endowing them with the glows and glories and final illustriousness which belong to every real thing, and to real things only. Without that ultimate vivification&#11840;which the poet or other artist alone can give&#11840;reality would seem incomplete, and science democracy, and life itself finally in vain.</p>
   <p>Few appreciate the moral revolutions, our age, which have been profounder far than the material or inventive or war-produced ones. The nineteenth century, now well towards its close (and ripening into fruit the seeds of the two preceding centuries<metamark target="#a008">*</metamark>),&#11840;the uprisings of</p>
   <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
   <metamark xml:id="a008" target="#a009">*</metamark><note type="authorial" place="bottom" xml:id="a009">The ferment and germination even of the United States to-day, dating back to, and in my opinion mainly founded on, the Elizabethan age in English his-</note>
   
   <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="tex_am.00018_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
   
   <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="tex_am.00019_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
   
   <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="tex_am.00020_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
   
   <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="tex_am.00021_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
   
   <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="tex_am.00008_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
   
   <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="tex_am.00009_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
   
   <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="tex_am.00010_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
   
   <pb xml:id="leaf007r" facs="tex_am.00011_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
   
   <pb xml:id="leaf007v" facs="tex_am.00012_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
   
</body>
</text>
</TEI>