<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="tex.00410"> 
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    
    <title level="m" type="main">Backward Glances over a Traveled road</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
    <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
    <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
    <editor>Matt Cohen</editor>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
     
     <persName xml:id="ew">Emma Whaley</persName>
    </respStmt>
    <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
    <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
    <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition>
     <date>2024</date>
    </edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    
    <distributor xml:id="wwa">The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
    <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
    <availability>
     <p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain exceptions, public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation of derivative works without permission, or authorization, of the former copyright owners.</p>
     <p>
      The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and is governed by a
      <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref>
      (CC BY 4.0). Permission to reproduce the graphic images of the original item has been granted by the owners of the original for this publication only.</p>
    </availability>
    

   <idno>tex.00410</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project" target="#dat1"><!-- THE CONTENTS OF THIS NOTE WILL BE WRITTEN BY EDITORS AT A LATER STAGE OF THE PROCESS --></note>
    
     <note type="work_relations" target="xxx.00410" cert="high">
      <p>Proof of "My Book and I" (with corrections), which is one of the essays that Whitman combined to form "A Backward Glance O'er Travel'd Roads," which first appeared in November Boughs (1888).</p>
     </note>
   </notesStmt>
   
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <author xml:id="ww">Whitman, Walt</author>
     
     <title>"Backward Glances over a Traveled Road" (see also Leaves of Grass), proof with corrections, undated, 7pp</title>  
     
     <date notBefore="1846" notAfter="1888" cert="medium"></date>
     
     <idno type="callno">	TXRC03-A4, series 1, container 1.2</idno>
     
     <orgName xml:id="tex">The Walt Whitman Collection, Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, The University of Texas at Austin</orgName>
     
     <note>Transcribed from digital images of the original.</note>
      
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <handNotes>
    <handNote medium="letterpress" xml:id="h01" resp="#unk1" scope="major"><name xml:id="unk1">Unknown 1</name></handNote>
    <handNote medium="black ink" xml:id="h02" resp="#ww" scope="minor"/>
    <handNote medium="pencil" xml:id="h03" resp="#unk2" scope="minor"><name xml:id="unk2">Unknown 2</name></handNote>
   </handNotes>
  </profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
 
 <change when="2025-02-05" who="#ew">transcribed and encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>

 <text type="manuscript">
  <body>
   
   <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="tex_am.00007_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
   
   <note type="archival" place="top" hand="#h03">f21- #15 File "A"</note>
   
   <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
   <note type="editorial" place="top">36</note>
   
   <head rend="italic"><subst hand="#h02"><del seq="1" rend="overstrike">MY BOOK AND I.</del><add seq="2" place="below" rend="underline">Backward Glances over a Traveled road</add></subst></head>
   <head type="sub" rend="italic">MY BOOK AND I.</head>
   
   <p>P<hi rend="smallcaps">ERHAPS</hi> the best of a song heard, or of any and all true love, or life's fairest episodes, or sailors', soldiers' trying scenes on land or sea, is the floating <hi rend="italic">r&#233;sum&#233;</hi> of them, or any of them, long afterwards, looking at the actualities away back past, with all their practical exci-tations gone. How the soul loves to hover over such reminiscences!</p>
   <p>So here I sit gossiping in the early candle-light of old age<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d001"><add place="right" hand="#h02"><metamark function="delete" target="#d001">d</metamark></add>,</del>&#8212;I and my book<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d002">,</del><add hand="#h02" place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d002">d</metamark></add>&#8212;casting backward glances over out travelled road. After completing, as it were, the journey (a varied jaunt of years, with many halts and gaps of intervals&#8212;or some lengthened ship-voyage, wherein more than once the last hour had apparently arrived, and we seemed certainly going down, yet reaching port<add hand="#h02" place="inline">,</add> in a <subst hand="#h02"><del seq="1" rend="overstrike">certain fashion</del><add seq="2" place="right">sufficient way,</add></subst> through all discomfitures at last)&#8212;after completing my poems, and letting an inter-val elapse to settle them, I am curious to review all in the light of their own (at the time unconscious, or mostly unconscious) intentions, with certain unfoldings of thirty years they seek to embody. These lines, therefore, will probably blend the weft of first purposes and speculations with the warp of that experience afterwards, always bring-ing strange developments.</p>
   <p>Result of seven or eight stages and struggles extending through nearly thirty years, I look upon "Leaves of Grass," now finished to the end of its opportunities and powers, as my definitive <hi rend="italic">carte <del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d003">de</del><add hand="#h02" place="right"><metamark function="delete" target="#d003">d</metamark></add> visite</hi> to the coming generations of the New World, <add place="above"><metamark target="#a001">*</metamark></add> if I may assume to say so. That I have not gained the acceptance of my own time, but have fallen back on fond dreams of the future ("Still lives the song, through Regnar dies")<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d004">,</del><add hand="#h02" place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d004">d</metamark></add>&#8212;that from a worldly and business point of view "Leaves of Grass" has been worse than a failure<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d005">,</del><add hand="#h02" place="right"><metamark function="delete" target="#d005">d</metamark></add>&#8212;that after thirty years of trial public criticism on the book and myself as author of it shows marked anger and contempt more than anything else ("I find a solid line of enemies to you everywhere,"&#8212;letter from W. S. K., Boston, May 28, 1884)<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d006">,</del><add hand="#h02" place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d006">d</metamark></add>&#8212;and that solely for publishing it I have been the object of two or three pretty serious official buffetings<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d007">,</del><add hand="#h02" place="right"><metamark function="delete" target="#d007">d</metamark></add>&#8212;is all probably no more than I ought to have expected. I had my choice when I commenced. I bid neither for soft eulogies, big money returns, nor the approbation of existing schools and conventions. As fulfilled, or partially fulfilled, the best comfort of the whole business (after a small band of the dearest
   <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
    
   <metamark target="#a002" xml:id="a001">*</metamark><note xml:id="a002" type="authorial" place="bottom">When Champollion, on his death-bed, handed to the printer the revised proof of his "Egyptian Grammar," he said gayly<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d008">,</del><add hand="#h02" place="right"><metamark function="delete" target="#d008">d</metamark></add> "Be careful of this,&#8212;it is my <hi rend="italic">carte de visite</hi> to posterity."</note>
    
    <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
   
   <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="tex_am.00014_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
   
   <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="tex_am.00015_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
    
    <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
    <note type="editorial" place="top"><hi rend="italic">MY BOOK AND I.</hi> 37</note>
   
   friends and upholders ever vouchsafed to man or cause<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d009">,</del><add hand="#h02" place="right"><metamark function="delete" target="#d009">d</metamark></add>&#8212;doubtless all the more faithful and uncompromising&#8212;this little phalanx!&#8212;for being so few) is that, unstopped and unwarped by any influence outside the soul within me, I have had my say entirely my own way, and put it unerringly on record<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d010">,</del><add hand="#h02" place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d010">d</metamark></add>&#8212;the value thereof to be decided by time.</p>
   <p>In calculating that decision, William O'Connor and Dr. Bucke are far more peremptory than I am. Behind all else that can be said, I consider "Leaves of Grass" and its theory experimental<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d011">,</del><add hand="#h02" place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d011">d</metamark></add>&#8212;as, in the deepest sense, I consider our American republic itself to be, with its theory. I think I have at least enough philosophy not to be too absolutely certain of any thing of any results. In the second place, the volume is a <hi rend="italic">sortie</hi><del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d012">,</del><add hand="#h02" place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d012">d</metamark></add>&#8212;whether to prove triumphant and conquer its field of aim and escape and construction, nothing less than a hundred years from now can fully answer. I consider the point that I have positively gained a hearing to far more than make up for any and all other lacks and withholdings. Essentially <hi rend="italic">that</hi> was from the first, and has remained throughout, the main object. Now it is achieved, I am certainly con-tent<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d013">ed</del><add hand="#h02" place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d013">d</metamark></add> to waive any otherwise momentous drawbacks, as of little account.</p>
   <p>After continued personal ambition and effort, as a young fellow, to enter with the rest into competition for the usual rewards, business, political, literary, etc.<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d014">,</del><add hand="#h02" place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d014">d</metamark></add>&#8212;to take part in the great <hi rend="italic">m&#234;l&#233;e</hi>, both for victory's prize itself and to do some good<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d015">,</del><add hand="#h02" place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d015">d</metamark></add>&#8212;after years of those aims and pursuits, I found myself remaining possessed, at the age of thirty-three to thirty-five, with a special desire and conviction. Or rather, to be quite exact, a desire and conviction that had been more or less flitting through my previous life, or hovering on the flanks, hitherto, had steadily advanced to the front, defined itself, and finally dominated everything else. This was a feeling or ambition to articulate and faithfully express in literary form<add hand="#h02" place="below"><metamark function="add" target="#a003">&#8248;</metamark></add><add hand="#h02" place="left" xml:id="a003">,<metamark function="emphasize" target="#a003">/</metamark></add> and uncompromisingly<add hand="#h02" place="below"><metamark function="add" target="#a004">&#8248;</metamark></add><add hand="#h02" place="right" xml:id="a004">,<metamark function="add" target="#a004">/</metamark></add> my own physical, emotional, moral, intellectual, and &#230;sthetic Personality, in the midst of, and tallying, the momentous spirit and facts of its immediate days and of current America<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d016">,</del><add hand="#h02" place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d016">d</metamark></add>&#8212;and to exploit that Personality in a far more candid and comprehensive sense than any hitherto book.</p>
   <p>Perhaps this is in brief<add hand="#h02" place="below"><metamark function="add" target="#a005">&#8248;</metamark></add><add hand="#h02" place="left" xml:id="a005">,<metamark function="emphasize" target="#a005">/</metamark></add> or suggests<add hand="#h02" place="below"><metamark function="add" target="#a006">&#8248;</metamark></add><add hand="#h02" place="left" xml:id="a006">,<metamark function="emphasize" target="#a006">/</metamark></add> all I have sought to do. Given the nineteenth century with the United States and what they furnish as area and points of view, "Leaves of Grass" is, or seeks to be, simply a faithful and doubtless self-willed record. In the midst of all it gives one man's&#8212;the author's&#8212;identity, ardors, observations, faiths, and thoughts, colored hardly at all with any<add hand="#h02" place="below"><metamark function="add" target="#a007">&#8248;</metamark></add><add hand="#h02" place="left" xml:id="a007">decided</add> coloring from other faiths, other authors, other identities or times. Plenty of songs had been sung<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d017">,</del><add hand="#h02" place="right"><metamark function="delete" target="#d017">d</metamark></add>&#8212;beautiful, matchless songs&#8212;adjusted to other lands than these&#8212;other days, another spirit and stage of evolution; but I would sing, and leave out or put
    
    <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
   
   <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="tex_am.000016_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
   
   <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="tex_am.00017_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
    
    <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
   <note type="editorial" place="top">38 <hi rend="italic">MY BOOK AND I.</hi></note>
    
    in, solely with reference to America and myself and to-day. Modern science and democracy seemed to be throwing out their challenge to Poetry to put them in its statements in contradistinction to the songs and myths of the past. As I see it now (perhaps too late<subst hand="#h02"><del seq="1" rend="overstrike">),</del><add seq="2" place="right" xml:id="a010">,)<metamark function="emphasize" target="#a010">/</metamark></add></subst> I have unwittingly taken up that challenge and made an attempt at such statements<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d018">,</del><add hand="#h02" place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d018">d</metamark></add>&#8212;which I certainly would not assume to do now, knowing more clearly what it means.</p>
   <p>For grounds for "Leaves of Grass," as poetry, I have abandoned the conventional themes, which do not appear in it<subst hand="#h02"><del seq="1" rend="overstrike">:</del><add seq="2" place="right" xml:id="a011">;<metamark function="emphasize" target="#a011">/</metamark></add></subst> none of the stock ornamentation, or choice plots of love or war, or high, exceptional personages of Old-World song; nothing, as I may say, for beauty's sake<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d019">,</del><add hand="#h02" place="right"><metamark function="delete" target="#d019">d</metamark></add>&#8212;no legend, or myth, or romance, nor euphemism, nor rhyme. But the broadest average of humanity and its identities in the now ripening <subst hand="#h02"><del seq="1" rend="overstrike">n</del><add seq="2" place="left">N</add></subst>ineteenth <subst hand="#h02"><del seq="1" rend="overstrike">c</del><add seq="2" place="left">C</add></subst>entury, and especially in each of their countless examples and practical occupations in the United States to day.</p>
   <p>One main contrast of the ideas behind every page of my verses, com-pared with established poems, is (as I have said once before) their different relative attitude towards God, towards the objective universe, and still more(by reflection, confession, assumption, etc.) the quite changed attitude of the ego, the one changing or talking, towards himself and towards his fellow-humanity. It is certainly time for America, above all, to begin this readjustment in the scope of verse, for everything else has changed. As I write, I see in an article on Wordsworth, in one of the current English magazines, the lines, "A few weeks ago an eminent French critic said that, owing to the special tendency to science and to its all-devouring force, poetry would cease to be read in fifty years." But I anticipate the very contrary. Only a firmer, vastly broader, new area begins to exist&#8212;nay, is already formed&#8212;to which the poetic genius must emigrate. Whatever may have been the case in years gone by, the true use for the imaginative faculty of modern times is to give ultimate vivification to facts, to science, and to common lives, endowing them with the glows and glories and final illustriousness which belong to every real thing, and to real things only. Without that ultimate vivification&#8212;which the poet or other artist alone can give&#8212;reality would seem incomplete, and science democracy, and life itself finally in vain.</p>
   <p>Few appreciate the moral revolutions, our age, which have been profounder far than the material or inventive or war-produced ones. The <subst hand="#h02"><del seq="1" rend="overstrike">n</del><add seq="2" place="left">N</add></subst>ineteenth <subst hand="#h02"><del seq="1" rend="overstrike">c</del><add seq="2" place="left">C</add></subst>entury, now well towards its close (and ripening into fruit the seeds of the two preceding centuries<ref xml:id="r1" target="#n1"><metamark function="link">*</metamark></ref>),&#8212;the uprisings of
   <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
    
   <note type="authorial" place="bottom" xml:id="n1" target="#r1" next="#n1.2"><metamark function="link">*</metamark><p>The ferment and germination even of the United States to-day, dating back to, and in my opinion mainly founded on, the Elizabethan age in English <choice><orig>his-</orig><reg>history</reg></choice></p></note>
    
    <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
   
   <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="tex_am.00018_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
   
   <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="tex_am.00019_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
   
    <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
   <note type="editorial" place="top"><hi rend="italic">MY BOOK AND I.</hi> 39</note>
   
   national masses and shifting of boundary-lines<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d020">,</del><add place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d020">d</metamark></add>&#8212;the historical and other prominent facts of the United States<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d021">,</del><add place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d021">d</metamark></add>&#8212;the Sucession War<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d022">,</del><add place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d022">d</metamark></add>&#8212;the stormy rush and hast of nebulous forces<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d023">,</del><add place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d023">d</metamark></add>&#8212;never can future years witness more excitement and din of action&#8212;never completer change of army front along the whole line, the whole civilized world. For all these new and evolutionary facts, meanings, purposes, new messages, new forms and expressions, are inevitable.</p>
   <p>My Book and I<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d024">,</del><add place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d024">d</metamark></add>&#8212;what a period we have presumed to span! those thirty years from 1850 to '80&#8212;and America in them! Proud, proud indeed my we be if we have culled enough of that period in its own spirit to worthily waft a few live breaths of it to the future!</p>
   <p>Let me not dare, here or anywhere, to attempt any definition of Poetry, nor answer the question what it is. Like Religion, Love, Nature, while those terms are indispensable, and we all give a sufficiently accurate meaning to them, no definition that has ever been made sufficiently encloses the name Poetry; nor can any rule or convention ever so absolutely obtain but some great exception may arise and disregard and overturn it.</p>
   <p>Also it must be carefully remembered that first-class literature does not shine by any luminosity of its own, nor do its poems. They grow of circumstances, and are evolutionary. The actual living light is al-ways from elsewhere<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d025">,</del><add place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d025">d</metamark></add>&#8212;follows unaccountable sources, and is lunar and relative at the best. There are, I know, certain controlling themes that seem endlessly appropriated to the poets<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d026">,</del><add place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d026">d</metamark></add>&#8212;as war, in the past<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d027">,</del><add place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d027">d</metamark></add>&#8212;in the Bible, religious rapture and adoration<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d028">,</del><add place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d028">d</metamark></add>&#8212;always love, beauty, some plot, or some pensive or other emotion. But, strange as it may sound at first, I will say there is something far deeper and towering far higher than those themes for the elements of modern song.</p>
   <p>Just as all the old imaginative works rest, after their kind, on ling trains of presuppositions, often entirely unmentioned by themselves, yet supplying the most important parts or bases of them, and without which they could have had no reason for being, so "Leaves of Grass," before a line was written, presupposed something different from any other, and as it stands is the result of such presupposition. I should say, indeed, it were useless to attempt reading the book without first carefully tallying that preparatory background <del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d029">and quality</del><add place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d029">d</metamark></add> in the mind. Think of the United States to-day&#8212;the facts of these thirty-eight or forty empires soldered in one&#8212;fifty or sixty millions of equals, with
    <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
    
   <note type="authorial" place="bottom" xml:id="n1.2" prev="#n1"><p><choice><orig>tory</orig><reg/></choice>, the age of Francis Bacon and Shak<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d030">e</del><add place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d030">d</metamark></add>spe<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d031">a</del><add place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d031">d</metamark></add>re. Indeed, when we pursue it, what growth or advent is there that does not date back, back, until it lost&#8212;perhaps its most tantalizing clues lost&#8212;in the receded horizons of the past?</p></note>
    
    <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
   
   <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="tex_am.00020_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
   
   <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="tex_am.00021_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
   
    <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
    <note type="editorial" place="top">40 <hi rend="italic">MY BOOK AND I.</hi></note>
   
   their lives, their passions, their future&#8212;these incalculable and seething multitudes around us, and of which we are inseparable parts! Think, in comparison, of the petty environage and limited area of the poets of past or present Europe, no matter how great their genius. Think of the absence and ignorance, in all cases hitherto, of the multitudinousness, vitality, and the unprecedented stimulants of to-day and here. It almost seems as if a poetry with anything like cosmic features were never possible before. It is certain that a poetry of absolute faith and equality for the use of the modern never was</p>
   <p>In estimating first-class song, a sufficient nationality, or, on the other hand, what may be called the negative and lack of it (as in Goethe's case, it sometimes seems to me<subst hand="#h02"><del seq="1" rend="overstrike">),</del><add seq="2" place="right" xml:id="a014">,)<metamark function="emphasize" target="#a014">/</metamark></add></subst> in often, if not always, the first element. One needs only a little penetration to see, at more or less removes, the material facts of their country and radius, with the coloring of the moods of humanity at the time, and its gloomy or hopeful prospects, behind all poets and each poet, and forming their birth-marks. I know very well that my "Leaves" could not possibly have emerged from any other era than the latter half of the <subst hand="#h02"><del seq="1" rend="overstrike">n</del><add seq="2" place="right">N</add></subst>ineteenth <subst hand="#h02"><del seq="1" rend="overstrike">c</del><add seq="2" place="left">C</add></subst>entury, nor any other land that America, and from the absolute triumph <gap reason="illegible" extent="two characters"/> the National Union arms.</p>
   <p>And whether my friends claim it for me or not, I know well enough, <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#ew">too,</unclear> that in respect to pictorial talent, dramatic situations, and especially <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#ew">in</unclear> verbal melody and all the conventional technique of poetry, not only the divine works that to-day stand ahead in the world's reading, but dozens more, transcend (some of them immeasurably transcend) all I have done, or could do. But it seemed to me, as the objects in <subst hand="#h02"><del seq="1" rend="overstrike">n</del><add seq="2" place="right">N</add></subst>ature, the themes of &#230;stheticism, and all special exploitations of the mind and should, involve not only their own inherent quality, but the quality, just as inherent and important, of <hi rend="italic">their point of view</hi>,<add place="inline"><ref xml:id="r2" target="#n2"><metamark function="link">*</metamark></ref></add> the time had come to reflect all themes and things, old and new, in the lights thrown on them by the advent of America and democracy&#8212;to chant those themes through the genesis and ensemble of to-day&#8212;and that such illustration and ensemble are the chief demands of America's prospective imaginative literature. Not to carry out, in the approved style, some choice plot or fancy, or fine thoughts, or incidents, or courtesies<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d032">,</del><add place="right"><metamark function="delete" target="#d032">d</metamark></add>&#8212;all of which has been done overwhelmingly and well, probably never to  be excelled<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d033">,</del><add place="right"><metamark function="delete" target="#d033">d</metamark></add>&#8212;but that while in such &#230;sthetic presentation of objects, passions, plots, thoughts, etc.,
   
   <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
   
   <note type="authorial" place="bottom" xml:id="n2" target="#r2"><metamark function="link"><add place="inline">*</add></metamark>According to Immanuel Kant, the essential reality, giving shape and significance to all the rest.</note>
   
   <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
   
   <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="tex_am.00008_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
   
   <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="tex_am.00009_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
   
   <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
   <note type="editorial" place="top"><hi rend="italic">MY BOOK AND I.</hi> 41</note>
   
   our lands and days do not want, and probably will never have, anything better than they already possess from the bequests of the past, it still remains to be said that there is even towards all those a subjective and democratic point of view appropriate to ourselves along, and to our new genius and environments, different from anything hitherto, and that such conception of current life and art is for us the only means of their assimilation consistent with the Western world.</p>
   <p>Indeed, and anyhow, to put it specifically, has not the time arrived when, for highest current and future aims, there must imperatively come a readjustment of the whole theory and nature of Poetry? The question is important, and I may turn the argument over and repeat it: Does not the best thought of our day conceive of a birth and spirit of song superior to anything past or present? To the effectual and moral consolidation of America<add place="below" hand="#h02"><metamark function="add" target="#a015">&#8248;</metamark></add><add hand="#h02" xml:id="a015" place="left">&#8212;<metamark function="emphasize" target="#a015">/</metamark></add> (already, as materially established, the greatest factor in known history, and far, far greater through what it preludes and necessitates, and is to be in future)&#8212;to conform with and build on the concrete realities and theories of the universe furnished by modern science, and the only irrefragable basis for anything, verse included&#8212;to root both influences in the emotional and imaginative action of our time and any time, and dominate all that precedes or opposes them&#8212;is not a radically new verteber of the best song indispensable?</p>
   <p>The New World receives with joy the poems of the antique, with European feudalism's rich fund of epics, plays, ballads&#8212;seeks not in the least to deaden or displace those voices from our present time and area&#8212;holds them indeed as indispensable studies, influences, records, comparisons. But though the dawn-dazzle of the sun of literature is in those poems for us of to-day&#8212;though the best parts of current character in nations, social groups, or any man's or woman's individuality, Old World or New, are from them&#8212;and though if I were asked to name the most precious bequest to American civilization from all the hitherto ages, I am not sure but I would name those old and less old songs ferried hither from east and west<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d034">,</del><add hand="#h02" place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d034">d</metamark></add>&#8212;some serious words and debits re-main; some acrid considerations demand a hearing. Of the great poems received from abroad and from the ages, and to-day enveloping and penetrating America, is there one that is consistent with these United States, or essentially applicable to them as they are and are to be? Is there one whose underlying basis is not a denial and insult to democracy? What a comment is forms, anyhow, on this era of literary fulfilment, with the splendid day-rise of science and resuscitation of history, that our chief religious and poetical works are not our own, but have been furnished by far-back ages out of their arriere and darkness, or, at most, twilight! What is there in those works that so imperiously and
   
   <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
   
   <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="tex_am.00010_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
   
   <pb xml:id="leaf007r" facs="tex_am.00011_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
   
    <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
    <note type="editorial" place="top">42 <hi rend="italic">MY BOOK AND I.</hi></note>
   
   scornfully dominates all our advancement, boasted civilization, and culture?</p>
   <p>even Shak<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d035">e</del><add hand="#h02" place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d035">d</metamark></add>spe<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d036">a</del><add hand="#h02" place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d036">d</metamark></add>re, who so suffuses current literature and art (which indeed have in most degrees grown out of him<subst hand="#h02"><del seq="1" rend="overstrike">),</del><add seq="2" place="left" xml:id="a016">,)<metamark function="emphasize" target="#a016">/</metamark></add></subst> he too belongs essentially to the buried past. Only he holds the proud distinction<add hand="#h02" place="below"><metamark function="add" target="#a017">&#8248;</metamark></add><add hand="#h02" place="right" xml:id="a017">,<metamark function="emphasize" target="#a017">/</metamark></add> for cer-tain important phases of that past, of being the loftiest of the singers life has yet given voice to. All, however, relate to and rest upon conditions, standards, politics, sociologies, ranges of belief, that have been quite eliminated from the Eastern hemisphere, and never existed at all in the Western. As authoritative types of song they belong in America just about as much as the persons and institutes they depict. True, it may be said, the emotional, moral, and &#230;sthetic natures of humanity have not changed&#8212;that in these the old poems apply to our times and all times, irrespective of date, and that they are of incalculable value as pictures of the past. I willingly make those admissions, and to their fullest extent; then advance the points herewith as of serious, even paramount importance.</p>
   <p>I have indeed put on record elsewhere my reverence and eulogy for those never-to-be-excelled poetic bequests, and their indescribable preciousness as heirlooms for America. Another and separate point must now be candidly stated. If I had not stood before those poems with uncovered head, fully aware of their colossal grandeur and beauty of form and spirit, I could not have written "Leaves of Grass." My verdict and conclusions as illustrated in its pages are arrived at through the temper and inculcation of the old works as much as through any-thing else<del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike" xml:id="d037">,</del><add hand="#h02" place="left"><metamark function="delete" target="#d037">d</metamark></add>&#8212;perhaps more than through anything else. As America fully and fairly construed is the legitimate result and evolutionary our-come of the past, so I would dare to claim for my verse. Without stopping to qualify the averment, the Old World has had the poems of myths, fictions, feudalism, conquest, caste, dynastic wars, and splendid exceptional characters and affairs, which have been great; but the New World needs the poems of realities and science<add hand="#h02" place="below"><metamark function="add" target="#a018">&#8248;</metamark></add><add hand="#h02" place="right" xml:id="a018">,<metamark function="emphasize" target="#a018">/</metamark></add> and of the democratic average and basic equality, which shall be greater. In the centre of all, and object of all, stands the Human Being, towards whose heroic and spiritual evolution poems and everything directly or indirectly tend, Old World or New.</p>
   
   <signed rend="italic"><del hand="#h02" rend="overstrike">Walt Whitman.</del></signed>
   
   <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
   <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
   
   <pb xml:id="leaf007v" facs="tex_am.00012_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
   
</body>
</text>
</TEI>