<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="yal.00323"> 
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    
    <title level="m" type="main">Preface</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
    <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
    <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
    <editor>Matt Cohen</editor>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
     
     <persName xml:id="ew">Emma Whaley</persName>
    </respStmt>
    <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
    <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
    <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition>
     <date>2024</date>
    </edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    
    <distributor xml:id="wwa">The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
    <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
    <availability>
     <p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain exceptions, public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation of derivative works without permission, or authorization, of the former copyright owners.</p>
     <p>
      The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and is governed by a
      <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref>
      (CC BY 4.0). Permission to reproduce the graphic images of the original item has been granted by the owners of the original for this publication only.</p>
    </availability>
    

   <idno>yal.00323</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project" target="#dat1"><!-- THE CONTENTS OF THIS NOTE WILL BE WRITTEN BY EDITORS AT A LATER STAGE OF THE PROCESS --></note>
    
    
     <note type="work_relations" target="xxx.00586" cert="high">
      <p>A corrected galley proof of Whitman's Preface to William Douglas O'Connor's <hi rend="italic">Three Tales</hi> (1892). Whitman included this preface in <hi rend="italic">Good-Bye My Fancy</hi> (1891) as "Preface to a volume of essays and tales by Wm. JD. O'Connor, pub'd posthumously in 1891."</p>
     </note>
   </notesStmt>
   
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <author xml:id="ww">Whitman, Walt</author>
     
     <title>Galley proof for "Preface" (In Series V)</title>  

     <date when="1890" cert="high"></date>
     
     <idno type="callno">YCAL MSS 202, box 13, folder 251</idno>

     <orgName xml:id="yal">Yale Collection of American Literature, Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library</orgName>
     
     <note>Transcribed from digital images of the original.</note>
      
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <handNotes>
    <handNote medium="letterpress" xml:id="h01" resp="#unk" scope="major"><name xml:id="unk">Unknown</name></handNote>
    <handNote medium="black ink" xml:id="h02" resp="#ww" scope="minor"/>
    <handNote medium="blue crayon" xml:id="h03" resp="#ww" scope="minor"/>
   </handNotes>
  </profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
 

 <change when="2024-12-04" who="#ew">transcribed and encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>

 <text type="manuscript">
  <body>
   
   <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="yal.00323.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
   
   <note type="authorial" hand="#h02" place="top" rend="circled">space this first col: with some<add place="above">a few</add>more double leads if you like&#8212;Let me have another proof please</note>
   <note type="authorial" hand="#h02" place="left" rend="circled">Walt Whitman Sept: 1890</note>
   
   <head rend="italic">Preface.</head>
   
   <p>A hasty memorandum, not particularly for Preface to the following tales but to put on record my respect and affection for as sane, beautiful, cute, tolerant, loving, candid and free and fair-intentioned a native as ever <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#ew">vibvified</unclear> our race.</p>
   <p> In Boston, 1860, I first met W<hi rend="smallcaps">ILLIAM</hi> D<hi rend="smallcaps">OU-GLAS</hi> O'C<hi rend="smallcaps">ONNOR</hi>.* As I saw and knew him then, in his 29th year, and for twenty-five further years, he was a gallant, handsome, gay-hearted, fine-voiced, glowing-eyed man; lithe-moving on his feet, of healthy and magnetic atmosphere and presence, and the most wel-come company in the world. He was a tho-rough-going anti-slavery believer, speaker and writer, (doctrinaire,) and though I took a fancy to him from the first, I remember I feared his ardent abolitionism&#8212;was afraid it would pro-baly keep us apart. (I was a decided and out-spoken anti-slavery believer myself, then aud always; but shy'd from the extremists, the red-hot fellows of those times.) H. O'C. was then correcting the proofs of <hi rend="italic">Harrington</hi>, an eloquent and fiery novel he had written, and what was written before the commencement of the Secession War. He was already mar-ried, the father of two fine little children, and was personally and intellectually the most at-tractive man I had ever met. I last of '62 found myself led towards the war-field&#8212;went to Washington City&#8212;to become absorb'd in the armies, and in the big hospitals, and to get work in one of the Departments,)&#8212;and there I met and resumed friendship and found warm hospitality from O'C. and his noble New England wife. They had just lost by death their little child-boy Philip; and O'C. was yet feeling serious about it. The youngster had been vaccinated against the threatening of small-pox which alarmed the city; but somehow it led to worse results than it was intended to ward off&#8212;or at any rate O'C. thought that proved the cause of the boy's death. He had one child left, a fine bright little daughter, and a great comfort to her parents. (Dear Jeannie! She grew up a most accomplished and superior young woman&#8212;declined in health, and died about 1881.)</p>
   <p></p>
   
   <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="yal.00323.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
   
</body>
</text>
</TEI>