<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="med.00725">
    <relations>
        <work ref="xxx.00480"><p>It is likely that some of these notes contributed to Whitman's article entitled "New Orleans in 1848," published in the New Orleans <hi rend="italic">Daily Picayune</hi> on January 25, 1887.</p></work>
    </relations>
     <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main" rend="bracketed">1848 New Orleans</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="es">Jeannette Schollaert</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.00725</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2014 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project" target="#dat1">These notes about Whitman's time in New Orleans (February through May, 1848) appear to be a combination of observations made at the time of his New Orleans soujorn and later recollections of that time. Because the manuscript has not been located it is difficult to speculate on the circumstances or date of its composition, but it seems likely that it was written at various times between 1848 and several years afterward. Edward Grier notes that "H." and "M'C." probably refer to publishers A. H. Hayes and J. E. McClure.</note>             
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>                
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                        <editor>Edward F. Grier</editor>
                        <title xml:id="nupm">Notebooks and Unpublished Prose Manuscripts</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                            <date when="1984">1984</date>
                            <biblScope type="page">86&#8211;87</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                    <note type="project">Grier derives his text from <hi rend="italic">The Uncollected Poetry and Prose of Walt Whitman</hi>, ed. Emory Holloway (Garden City, NY: Doubleday, Page &amp; Co., 1921), 2:77&#8211;78.</note>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title rend="bracketed">1848 New Orleans</title>                  
                    <date xml:id="dat1" notBefore="1848" notAfter="1855">Between 1848 and 1855</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of this manuscript is unknown.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-05-20" who="#km">checked</change>
            <change when="2016-02-16" who="#es">checked, added date to bibl (from finding aid information)</change>
            <change when="2014-10-18" who="#jc">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="manuscript">
        <body>
            <p>1848 New Orleans/ March 18th. We have now been publishing "the <hi rend="italic">Crescent</hi>," two weeks; and it seems to be going ahead handsomely. My situation is rather a pleasant one. I get through at evening much earlier than I had anticipated, which I like, of course, very well. There are many peculiarities in New Orleans that I shall jot down at my leisure in these pages. It seems somewhat strange that I have not heard from home. It is now over a month, and no letter yet.</p>
            
            <p>(I arrived in New Orleans, on the night of Friday Feb. 25th; and left it Saturday afternoon, May 27th, '48.)</p>
            
            <p>On board steamer <hi rend="italic">Griffith</hi> Upper part of Lake Huron, Saturday morning, June 10th, 1848.</p>
            
            <p>For a few weeks after I commenced my duties at New Orleans, matters went on very pleasantly. People seemed to treat me kindly, particularly H. and M'C. My health was most capital; I frequently thought indeed that I felt better than ever before in my life. After changing my boarding house, Jef. and I were, take it altogether, pretty comfortable. We had good beds, and though the noise was incessant, day and night, we slept well. The plan of going to dinner when we liked, and calling for what we wanted, out of a variety of dishes, was more convenient than the usual way of boarding houses.</p>
            
            <p>Through some unaccountable means, however, both H. and M'C, after a while, exhibited a singular sort of coldness, toward me, and the latter an irritability toward Jef., who had, at times, much harder work than I was willing he should do.</p>
            
            <p>The arrangements of the office were in this wise: I generally went about my work about 9 o'clock, overhauling the papers <choice><abbr>rec'd</abbr><expan>received</expan></choice> by mail, and "making up the news," as it is called, both with pen and scissors. A Mr. Larue (a good writer,) generally prepared the leading editorials; Mr. Reeder, (an amiable-hearted young man, but excessively intemperate) was the "city news" man; (poor Reeder is dead, since) and a young fellow named <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#nupm" cert="medium">Da Poute</unclear>, officiated as translator of Mexican and foreign n&#8212;items; factotum in general. I had been accustomed to having frequent conferences, in my former situations with the proprietors of newspapers, on the subject of management, etc. But when the coldness above alluded to broke out, H. seemed to be studiously silent upon all these matters. My own pride was touched&#8212;and I met their conduct with equal haughtiness on my part. On Wednesday May 24th I sent down a note requesting a small sum of money. M'C returned me a bill of what money I had already drawn, and stated that they could not make "advances." I answered by reminding them of certain points which appeared to have been forgotten, making me <hi rend="italic">not</hi> their debtor, and told them in my reply I thought it would be better to dissolve the connection. They agreed to my plan (after some objections on the part of me); and I determined to leave on the succeeding Saturday.</p>
            
            <p>Accordingly on Friday I packed up my traps, and <gap reason="cut away"/></p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
