<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?> <?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?> 
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nyp.00018">
   <relations>
      <work ref="xxx.00259" cert="high">
         <p>This manuscript is a draft (or, less likely, a later version) of <ref target="loc.00216.html">loc.00216</ref>, which was originally inscribed as part of the early manuscript poem <ref target="yal.00081.html">"Pictures."</ref> The first several lines of "Pictures" were revised and published as "My Picture-Gallery" in the 30 October 1880 issue of <hi rend="italic">The American</hi>. The poem was later published in <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> as part of the "Autumn Rivulets" cluster (1881, p. 310)</p>
      </work>
   </relations>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main" rend="bracketed">The shower of meteors</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor role="editor">Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <editor role="editor">Ed Folsom</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="cah">Caitlin Henry</persName>
               <persName xml:id="bb">Brett Barney</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2019</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>nyp.00018</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>The text of the original item is in the public domain. The text encoding and editorial notes were created and/or prepared by the <hi rend="italic">Walt Whitman Archive</hi> and are licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0). Any reuse of the material should credit the <hi rend="italic">Walt Whitman Archive</hi>. Permission to reproduce the graphic images of the original item has been granted by the owners of the original for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>                       
            <note type="project" target="dat1">This manuscript is written in the bottom margin of a page clipped from the September 1849 issue of <hi rend="italic">Sartain's Union Magazine of Literature and Art</hi>. Whitman probably wrote this note in the early 1850s, before the appearance of the first edition of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> in 1855. It is a draft (or, less likely, a later version) of lines that appear in <ref target="loc.00216.html">loc.00216</ref>, which was originally inscribed as part of the early manuscript poem "Pictures" (<ref target="yal.00081.html">yal.00081</ref>). Harold W. Blodgett and Sculley Bradley see "Pictures" as "an important preliminary, a kind of auspice of <hi rend="italic">LG</hi> 1855" that shows Whitman's early attempts to turn his experiences and reading into verse. They note that Whitman apparently returned to the manuscript repeatedly over several decades and eventually reworked its first several lines as "My Picture-Gallery," a poem he published in the 30 October 1880 issue of <hi rend="italic">The American</hi>. See Blodgett and Bradley, eds., <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass: Comprehensive Reader's Edition</hi> (New York: New York University Press, 1965), 642&#8211;649.</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Holograph memoranda and notes, unsigned and undated, written on 27 scraps of paper
</title>
               <date cert="medium" notBefore="1849" notAfter="1860" xml:id="dat1">Between 1849 and 1860</date>
               <idno type="callno">b15520479</idno> <!--MSS Unit ID: 19100; Other local identifier: 175226b; Archives EAD ID: 949125; Universal Unique Identifier (UUID): 4ae6d720-a46c-0130-a047-3c075448cc4b -->
               <orgName xml:id="nyp">The Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature, New York Public Library</orgName> 
               <note type="project">Transcribed from digital images of the original.</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="#bb" when="2019-06-03">corrected publication date of Comprehensive Reader's Edition, based on Ken's review</change>
         <change who="#bb" when="2019-05-08">checked; edited</change>
         <change who="#cah" when="2019-02-15">transcribed; encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>

         <pb facs="nyp_ch.00007_large.jpg" xml:id="leaf001r" type="recto"/> 
					          
           <p>The shower of meteors&#8212;This occurred in the night of 12th&#8209;13th Nov. 1833&#8212;toward morning&#8212; &#8212;myriads in all directions, some with long shining white trains, some falling over each other like falling water&#8212;leaping, silent, white, <del rend="overstrike">the</del> apparitions around up there in the sky <add rend="insertion" place="top">over my head.</add></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
